Let's look at the answer to our quiz
about the relationship between the block
size and the miss rate. The question was
which of the three C's are really
reduced when the miss rate goes down?
Obviously, some misses have been
eliminated. The question is which type
suffered the elimination? Let's first
look at the compulsory misses. If we
have a small block size, and this is our
memory, we'll bring in this block and
suffer a miss for the first time. We
bring in another block and suffer a
miss. Now, let's say we bring in this
block and suffer a miss.
If the cache line size was twice of what
it is now,
then the second one would not have been
a miss because when we fetch the first
one,
the second one would have also been in
the same cache block. So, as you can
see, the increase in the block size,
assuming there is enough locality, will
result in a reduction in compulsory
misses. Another way to look at this is
to note that we get a compulsory miss
when we access the block for the very
first time. Well, if you have larger
blocks, there are fewer blocks, so there
are fewer blocks to access for the very
first time, and that will guarantee a
reduction in compulsory misses, assuming
there is any spatial locality. Now,
let's look at capacity misses. Let's say
that the program is accessing a
relatively large array that doesn't fit
in the cache, and then
we go back and access it again. On the
second set of accesses, we're having
capacity misses.
The first set of accesses were
compulsory misses because these blocks
were never in the cache. Because they
don't fit in the cache, by the time we
get to the end of the array,
the beginning of the array is kicked out
of the cache, and now we're suffering
capacity misses. These blocks would be
in the infinite cache.
They're not in the cache because it was
not large enough. But how many misses we
will have for this array depends on the
block size. With smaller blocks, the
same size array would be occupying more
blocks. With larger blocks, we will have
fewer blocks. The number of misses will
be equal to the number of blocks. So, as
you can see, if we increase the block
size
and our miss rate goes down because
there is plenty of spatial locality,
we are also reducing the number of
capacity misses. And finally, if we look
at the conflict misses, we can construct
a similar example where two blocks are
kicking each other out. And because each
time we fetch a larger block, if the
block size goes up, we will be having
fewer conflict misses. So, the increase
in block size
can improve all types of misses. That
is, it can reduce the number
for all three types of misses. When we
increase the block size, the compulsory
misses are almost always going to go
down. The capacity misses are going to
go down as long as there is enough
locality, and the conflict misses are
likely to stay similar, but might go
down.